[
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 1,
        "year": 2017,
        "question": "<p><strong>a. </strong>what is  a legitimate government</p><p><strong>b.</strong> Outline any four features of legitimacy</p>",
        "answer": "<p><strong>a </strong>A legitimate government is one which is acceptable to the people either because it has been lawfully established or through its performance over a period of time.</p><p><strong>b</strong>(i).<strong> Legality: </strong>Government comes to power through lawful means</p><p>(ii). <strong>Acceptability</strong>: It is a government that is acceptable by the people</p><p>(iii). <strong>Recognition: </strong>It should be recognised both internally and externally</p><p>(iv). <strong>Popularity: </strong>It should be able to receive popular support from the people</p><p>(v). Accountability &amp; Transparency/ good governance: it should be able to be accountable and open in all its activities</p><p>(vi). Satisfaction of the needs of the people</p><p>(vii). Periodic free and fair elections: it should be able to conduct free and fair elections</p><p>(viii). Constitutionalism: It should adhere to the provisions of the constitution</p><p>(ix). Mechanism to check arbitrariness, impartial judicial system e.g Ombudsman, vibrant civil soci-ety organisations etc.</p><p>(x). Responsiveness to the people's views and opinions</p><p>(xi). Respect for rules and regulations, customs and traditions</p><p>(xii). Respect for fundamental human right</p><p>(xiii). Existence of rule of law</p><p>(xiv). Existence of free press</p><p>(xv). Popular participation-willingly taking part in all political activities e.g Registration, Rallies, voting etc. </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 2,
        "year": 2017,
        "question": "<p> (a) What are rights?</p><p>(b) Highlight four limitations on the rights of a citizen</p>",
        "answer": "<p><strong>a. </strong>Rights are legal entitlements that citizens of a state enjoy</p><p><strong>b.</strong> i. Legal limitations e.g. libel, slander, sedition etc <br>\n(ii). Declaration of a state of emergency</p><p>(iii). Public servant under oath of secrecy have no right to release official information</p><p>(iv). Remand/imprisonment by a court of competent jurisdiction.</p><p>(v). Restriction for health reasons e.g outbreak of contagious diseases</p><p>(vi). Violation of the rights of others</p><p>(vii). Illiteracy, poverty and ignorance</p><p>(viii). For the purpose of maintaining state security/Restricted areas</p><p>(ix). Insanity-lunatics are confined</p><p>(x). Acquisition of individual's property by the state for public use</p><p>(xi). Negative traditional practices can limit the right of the individual</p><p>(xii). The nature and system of government e.g Military</p><p>xiii. Economic and social conditions may limit the enjoyment of rights</p><p>(xiv). Constitutional limitations-public and civil servants are not allowed to participate in politics, age limitation in voting etc.</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 3,
        "year": 2017,
        "question": "<p>(a) Differentiate between a de jure and de-facto one-party system</p><p>(b) Outline four advantages of a multi-party system </p>",
        "answer": "<p><strong>a.</strong> De-jure: only one party is legally and official recognized in the state while in defactor other parties may exist but only one party dominates the political scene</p><p><strong>b.</strong> i. It is democratic because the people have the freedom to join any party of their choice</p><p>(ii). There is room for opposition which guarantees good governance</p><p>(iii). It checks arbitrary use of power</p><p>(iv). The electorate has a wide range of choosing leaders/policies or programmes</p><p>(v). It enhances wider political education</p><p>(vi). It ensures political accountability and transparency</p><p>(vii). It caters for the interest of the minority</p><p>(viii). Encourages healthy competition among the various political parties</p><p>(ix). It caters for all shades of political opinions</p><p>(x). It reflects genuinely the political differences that exist in a given society or state</p><p>(xi). It enhances political participation.</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 4,
        "year": 2017,
        "question": "<p>(a) What is a simple majority system?</p><p>(b) Outline four demerits of the system.</p>",
        "answer": "<p><strong>a.</strong> This is an electoral system in which the candidate with the highest number of votes is declared the winner in an election </p><p><strong>b.</strong> i. Sometimes it works against the wishes of the majority of the voters</p><p>ii. Smaller parties have little chance of winning election.</p><p>iii. The system does not reflect clearly the strength of the political parties.</p><p>iv. It is undemocratic because the combined votes of losers may exceed that of the winner</p><p>v. It gives a wrong impression about the popular-ity and legiimacy of the winner</p><p>vi. It promotes ethnicity in national politics</p><p>vii. It may encourage the election of mediocre candidates</p><p>viii. It is easier,to Manipulate/rig elections conducted under this system</p><p>ix. It gives room for gerrymandering </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 5,
        "year": 2017,
        "question": "<p> Identify five ways which the central government can improve upon local government system in West Africa.</p>",
        "answer": "<p> i. Increasing central government grants to local authorities for developmental projects</p><p>ii. The ministry of Local Government should evolve action plan for local authorities to generate revenue internally</p><p>iii. Minimizing central government interference and partisanship in local government administration</p><p>iv. Improvement of service conditions of local government workers in order to attract highly skilled personnel</p><p>v. Providing funds to organize refresher courses and in-service training for workers</p><p>vi. Effective internal and external auditing of ac-counts</p><p>vii. Effective ministerial control to avoid misappropriation and misapplication as well as misallocation <br>\nof funds <br>\nviii. Provision of adequate logistics for local authorities e.g. vehicles, furniture and computer facilities</p><p>ix. Assembly/Council members should be democratically elected to serve the interest of the people</p><p>x. Transparent appointment of local government administrators</p><p>xi. Application of technology in the operations of the Local Government system</p><p>xii. Granting of financial autonomy to the local government unit</p><p>xiii. The central government should scrutinize all loans contracted by local government</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 6,
        "year": 2017,
        "question": "<p>Functions performed by the Ogboni Secret Society in the pre-colonial Yoruba political system. </p>",
        "answer": "<p> i. Policy making: It was involved in the policy making process</p><p>ii. Religious function: It served as an intermediary between the people and their ancestors</p><p>iii. It approved decisions of the paramount ruler and his advisers</p><p>iv. Maintenance of law and order: It maintained law and order</p><p>v. Checks and balances: It checked the arbitrary use of powers by the ruler</p><p>vi. Protection: It provided protection for its members and the people</p><p>vii. It preserved the cultural values and heritage of the people</p><p>viii. It served as a final court of appeal in both civil and criminal cases</p><p>ix. It served as an agent of political education for the people</p><p>x. It helped in the dethronement or deposition of then ruler</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 7,
        "year": 2017,
        "question": "<p>(a) What is a crown colony?</p><p>(b) Highlight four functions of the Secretary of State for the colony under the British colonial system. </p>",
        "answer": "<p>(a) A crown colony is a territory acquired by the British monarch through settlement, cession, conquest or purchase</p><p>(b) i. Advising the colonial government on the appointment of governors</p><p>ii. Formulation of policies and programmes for the colony subject to British parliament approval</p><p>iii. Advising governors on formulation of policies in their respective colonies</p><p>iv. Supervision of the colonies</p><p>v. Approval of budget prepared by the governor</p><p>vi. Receiving delegation/petitions from the colonies</p><p>vii. Setting up.commission of enquiry into issues affecting the colonies</p><p>viii. Promotion, transfer and dismissal of governors</p><p> ix. Approving draft constitutions prepared by the governors</p><p>x. Controlling governor's veto and certification powers</p><p>xi. Submitting annual report about the colony to the British parliament</p><p>xii. Approved all major projects to be undertaken in the colonies</p><p>xiii. Issued orders and instructions to the Governors on British colonial policies.</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 8,
        "year": 2017,
        "question": "<p>Highlight five contributions of Herbert Macaulay to the political development of Nigeria.</p>",
        "answer": "<p>i. He championed the cause of the chiefs and people of Lagos against the Lagos High Court over land ownership</p><p>ii. Supported labour unions to organise strikes and rallies and fight for their rights</p><p>iii. He was the first to establish political party in Nigeria-the Nigeria National Democratic Party (NNDP) in 1922</p><p>iv. He was the first National president of National Council of Nigeria and the Cameroons (NCNC)</p><p>v. He was the father of all the Nigerian nationalist leaders. He was a rallying point for nationalists.</p><p>vi. He was instrumental to the establishment of Nigerian wing of National Council of British West Africa (NCBWA)</p><p>vii. He founded the Lagos Daily Newspaper</p><p>viii. He led a protest against the 1946 Richards Constitution</p><p>ix. He represented Nigeria in various constitutional conferences</p><p>x. He led his party, NNDP to win elections in the Lagos Municipal Council between 1923-38</p><p>xi. He joined other nationalist leaders to write petitions to the Colonial Office in London to com-plain about the evils of colonialism <br>\nxii. His activities led to the introduction of the Elective Principle in Nigeria.</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 9,
        "year": 2017,
        "question": "<p>(a) What is foreign policy?</p><p>(b) State four factors that influence Nigeria's foreign policy. </p>",
        "answer": "<p><strong>(a)</strong> Foreign policy is the principles, guidelines and strategy adopted by a country in conducting her relationship with other states while pursuing her national interest.</p><p><strong>(b)</strong>i. Africa centred: Africa is regarded as the centre-piece of Nigerian foreign policy</p><p>ii. Historical/Colonial background and experience</p><p>iii. Types of government e.g. military or democratic government</p><p>iv. Population: large size and the quality of human resources of Nigeria affect her foreign policy</p><p>v Ideological disposition of the leaders: Nigeria relates more with those countries that share similar ideologies</p><p>vi. The economic resources available to Nigeria e.g mineral resources and agricultural products</p><p>vii. Commitment to international laws, treaties and conventions</p><p>viii. Public opinion on issues can bring changes in government's foreign policy</p><p>ix. The industrial strength of Nigeria influences her choice of trading partners</p><p>x. Membership and commitment to international organisations</p><p>xi. The military strength of Nigeria e.g. the size and quality of the army influence her foreign policy</p><p>xii. The activities of interest/pressure groups influence Nigeria's foreign policy</p><p>xiii. Geographical location influences Nigeria's foreign policy</p><p>xiv. The desire for foreign investments and overseas market</p><p>xv. The personality of the leaders <br>\nxvi. National interest of Nigeria</p><p>xvii. Religious and ethnic factors</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 10,
        "year": 2017,
        "question": "<p>Outline any five contribution of Nigeria towards the growth of Economic Community of West African States (ECOWAS) </p>",
        "answer": "<p>i. Nigeria played an active role in the information of Economic Community of West African States (ECOWAS) as well as being an initial signatory to the Lagos Treaty</p><p>ii. Provision of high profile personnel for the ECOWAS Secretariat/agencies since its inception</p><p>iii. Nigeria Heads of State had served as chairman of ECOWAS</p><p>iv. Nigeria has played major roles in peace-keeping operations in Liberia, Sierra Leone and Coted'lvoire</p><p>v. Nigeria regularly attends all ECOWAS summits. </p><p>vi. Nigeria contributes to the development of ECOWAS by hosting summits and conferences</p><p>vii. Nigeria makes available petroleum products to other ECOWAS countries in need</p><p>viii. Membership of ECOWAS Parliament makes Nigeria to contribute to sub-regional issues</p><p>ix. Financial contribution: Nigeria pays her dues regularly to both the Secretariat and the ECOWAS Fund</p><p>x. Actively participates in ECOWAS sponsored activities like trade fair, sports etc</p><p>xi. Gives humanitarian assistance to citizens of ECOWAS countries who have been displaced as a result of war</p><p>xii. Implementation of ECOWAS protocols e.g the protocol in democracy and good governance, protocol on the fight against corruption etc</p><p>xiii. Nigeria has joined other ECOWAS countries in undertaking key projects e.g West African Gas Pipeline</p><p>xiv. Nigeria has allowed free movement of ECOWAS citizens, goods and services</p><p>xv. Sending officials to monitor elections in member states. </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    }
]